Patrick J. McPartlan

(847)-4#1-37#1 pjmcpartlan@wisc.edu

An enthusiastic and hardworking individual with a B.S. in Environmental Science, a certification in GIS and three years of professional experience at the Kane-DuPage Soil & Water Conservation District (KDSWCD). Patrick is a certified professional in soil erosion/sediment control, stormwater inspecting and Geographical Information Systems. He also has professional expertise in agriculture conservation planning, Clean Water Act implementation, remote sensing, watershed planning, drainage water management, green infrastructure, youth education, presenting, ecological restoration, concrete construction and computer programming. Patrick is seeking to expand upon his current master's degree pursuit in GIS and Web Map Development with the University of Wisconsin-Madison. Patrick's long-term goals are to design and implement regenerative agriculture principles at a large scale.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

KANE-DUPAGE SOIL & WATER CONSERVATION DISTRICT Resource Conservationist – GIS Specialist

St. Charles, IL October 2019 – Present

- Manage and Develop data for the Land Use Opinion (LUO) Report
- Manage Soil Erosion and Sediment Control (SESC) program
- Oversee Illinois Department of Agriculture Cost-share program
- Serve as Grant Administrator for the Illinois Urban Manual Program
- Hire and supervise Resource Analyst position
- Coordinate yearly soil erosion and sediment control seminar
- Participate in watershed working groups throughout the two counties
- Perform all roles from previous position

Resource Analyst – GIS Specialist

September 2017 – October 2019

- Manage GIS Operations, including; SESC and LUO database inventory, LUO map exports, historical aerial imagery service, certified conservation planning mapping, research data and software troubleshooting
- Manage SESC programs in Aurora, Batavia and North Aurora (MOUs)
- Perform NPDES ILR10 compliance inspections throughout Kane County on behalf of the IEPA
- Perform CWA Section 404 compliance inspections and plan reviews on behalf of the USACE within MOUs
- Perform day-to-day office operations and provide assistance with IT problems
- Participate in all KDSWCD special programs offered (Ag Days, Envirothon, Fish Sale, Plant Sales, etc.)

DEPARTMENT OF NATURAL RESOURCES

Des Moines, IA

Water Quality Intern

September 2016 – May 2017

Prepare and handle Time of Transfer (TOT) inspection reports for electronic storage record keeping

- Participate in NPDES industrial permit development meetings implementing requirements of the Clean Water Act
- Update the public Iowa Beverage Container Redemption Center list for the Solid Waste Sector of the LQB

REIMAN GARDENS

Ames, IA

Greenhouse Gardener

January 2017 - May 2017

CONSERVATION LAND STEWARDSHIP (DAVEY TREE)

Elmhurst, IL

Restoration Technician

June 2015- August 2015 | June 2016- August 2016

EDUCATION

University of Wisconsin-Madison

Online

Masters of GIS and Web Map Development

January 2020 - Present

COLLEGE OF DUPAGE

Glen Ellyn, IL

Certification in Geographical Information Systems (Geography Department)

August 2017 - May 24, 2019

Certification Capstone Project: Modeling Flood Susceptibility for Rural Regions Using Remote Sensing Applications

IOWA STATE UNIVERSITY

Ames, IA

Bachelor of Science in Environmental Science (College of Agriculture and Life Sciences)

August 2014 - May 2017

ADDITIONAL INFORMATION

- Technical Skills: ArcGIS, Adobe Acrobat/Illustrator/Photoshop, Microsoft Office 365, QGIS, ArcGIS Pro, Google Earth/Maps, WebSoilSurvey, SW Maps, HEC-RAS, WordPress, Python, GDAL, OGR, AutoCAD and Mapbox.
- Committee Participation: Illinois Urban Manual, Chicago Wilderness Oak Ecosystem Recovery Group, Illinois Mycological Society, CMAP Environmental and Natural Resource, Kane County GIS User Group, Kane County Stormwater Committee, Illinois Nutrient Loss Reduction Strategy Urban Stormwater Working Group
- Presentations: Geospatial Applications in Stormwater Pollution Prevention Plans at Stormwater Solutions Conference (11/19), Land Use Opinion Report at the Chicago Metropolitan Agency for Planning Environmental and Natural Resource Committee (9/20), Illinois Urban Manual Overview at East Branch DuPage River Watershed Webinar (5/20)
- Volunteer Experience: Hurricane Maria Mapping Project, Elgin Sustainability Committee, Missing Maps, VESA Ecuador 2016